Engineers and Scientists of America Records 5574
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Engineers and Scientists of America Records
1952-1960
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Engineers and Scientists of America
5574
21 cubic feet
21 linear ft.
Records (documents), case files.
Collection consists of, historical documents, Executive Board, Officer, and financial records, Convention documents, local/member society files, subject files, publications and photographs.
5665296
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 21, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 18, 2019
Scope and Contents
This collection is arranged by office of origin and alphabetically by subject thereunder.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Engineers -- United States; Scientists -- United States; Engineers and Scientists of America.
5665296
- Historical Documents Executive Board Records (Box 1)
  - History - Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ESA Introduction (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ESA Founding Material (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ESA Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Committee Meeting - September 27-28, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee 1952-53, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (2/23/1953) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (5/23-24/1953) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Special Executive Committee Meeting (8/22/1953) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (10/24-25/1953) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ESA Executive Committee Meeting (2/20-22/1954) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - ESA Executive Committee Meeting (4/25/1954) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Meeting (9/25-26/1954) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board Meetings, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Executive Board Meetings, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Executive Board Meetings, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Board Meetings, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Officers Records Amann, Joseph through Lightner, Leo F. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Federal Agencies, 1952-1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Amman, Joseph, Articles and Speeches (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Basci, Joseph (Executive Committeeman) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Buckius, Orland (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Dana, Benton P. (Executive Committeeman) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gardiner, E.M. (Executive Committeeman) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - James, Ricker (Assistant Publicity Director) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lightner, Leo F. (Washington Representative), 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Officers Records Mayer, Henry (Box 3)
  - Mayer, Henry (Attorney and Lobbyist), Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mayer, Henry, Monthly Reports, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Officers Records Mayer, Henry through Orth, A.A. (Box 4)
  - Mayer, Henry, Monthly Reports plus index, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Moore, Ray P. (Committeeman) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Orth, A.A. (Vice President) (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Officers Records Shuman, Lloyd through Weck, Herman I. (Box 5)
  - Shuman, Lloyd (Treasurer) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Stosskopf, George (Committeeman) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Taft, John E. (Vice President) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Weck, Herman I. (Treasurer) (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Financial Records Convention Documents Proceedings 1951-1953 (Box 6)
  - Financial Data, 1952-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1 Bound Volume Proceedings, 1953-1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Exploratory Conference of Engineers' Unions for National Organization, 1951" (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Proceedings, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Convention Documents Proceedings 1954-1958 (Box 7)
  - Proceedings, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Proceedings, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Proceedings, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Proceedings, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Proceedings, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Convention Documents Tapes of Conventions and Executive Board Minutes (Box 8)
  - Tapes of Conventions and Executive Board Minutes (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Convention Documents Tapes of Conventions and Executive Board Minutes (Box 9)
  - Tapes of Conventions and Executive Board Minutes (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Member/Society Files American Association of Engineers through Convair (Box 10)
  - American Association of Engineers (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Association of Professional Engineers, Scientists and Chemists (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Association of Industrial Scientists (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Association of Engineers and Engineering Assistants (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Association of Westinghouse Salaried Employees (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Association of Engineering Employees of Oregon (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Association of Professional Engineering Personnel Aerojet (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - American Telephone and Telegraph Association of Communication Engineers (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Scope and Contents
    Originally listed as "American Tele. And Tele. Assn. of Communication Engineers"
  - Association of Professional Engineers of the Province of Ontario (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Belock Instrument Corporation (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Bell Aircraft Engineers Association (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Conference of Professional Technical Personnel (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Conair (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Member/Society Files Council of Western Electric Professional Employees through Engineers Association of ARMA (Box 11)
  - Council of Western Electric Professional Employees (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Council of Western Electric Technical Employees (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Engineers and Architects Association (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Engineers Association of ARMA (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Member/Society Files Engineering Employees Association of Northern Electric through Leland Electric Company (Box 12)
  - Engineering Employees Association of Northern Electric (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Engineering Manpower Committee of Engineers, Joint Council (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Engineers and Scientists of California (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Engineers and Technical Employees (Sperry) (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Engineers Guild of Oregon (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Engineers and Scientists Guild (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Evendale Engineers Association (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Federation of Arsenal Engineers (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Fellows Gear Company (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Ford Motors - Aircraft Engineers Division (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fort Wayne Association - General Electric Engineers (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - General Electric Engineers Council (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Illinois Association of Highway Engineers (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - International Society of Skilled Trades (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Jersey Central Power and Light (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Leeds and Northrup Engineers Association (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Leland Electric Company (Box 12, Folder 17)
- Member/Society Files Mack Truck Engineers through Minneapolis Federation of Honeywell Engineers (Box 13)
  - Mack Truck Engineers (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - McDonnel Aircraft (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Menasco Manufacturing Company (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Minneapolis Federation of Honeywell Engineers (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Member/Society Files National Cash Register through Pittsfield General Electric Engineers Association (Box 14)
  - National Cash Register (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - National Independent Union Council (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - National Lead Company of Ohio (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - National Society of Professional Engineers (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - National Professional Association of Engineers, Architects and Scientists (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - New York City Engineers (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - New York State Society of Professional Engineers (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - North American Aircraft (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Oregon Professional Engineering Employees Association (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Otis Elevator (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania Power and Light (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Philco (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Pittsfield General Electric Engineers Association (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Member/Society Files Railway Technical Engineers through Seattle Professional Engineering Employees Association (Box 15)
  - Railway Technical Engineers (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Republic Engineers Association (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Research and Engineers Professional Employees Association (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Salaried Employees Association (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Schenectady General Electric Engineers Association (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Seattle Professional Engineering Employees Association (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Member/Society Files Society of American Military Engineers through TVA Engineers Association (Box 16)
  - Society of American Military Engineers (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Society of Engineering Employees (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Society of Engineers (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Society of Professional Chemists and Engineers (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Southern California Professional Engineering Association (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Sperry-Farragut (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Stanley Aviation Engineers Association (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Stewart Warner Company (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Syracuse General Electric Engineers Association (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Technical Engineers Association (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Technical Association of Ward Leonard (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - TVA Engineers Association (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Member/Society Files Union Electric Engineers Association through Yorko Engineering Division Subject Files Committee on Engineering Laws through Job Evaluation (Box 17)
  - Union Electric Engineers Association (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - West Coast Aircraft Engineers (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Westinghouse Engineers Association (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Western Electric (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Western Union (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Wichita Engineering Association (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Wood River Engineers (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - York Engineering Division (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Committee on Engineering Laws (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Education (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Engineers Joint Council (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Job Evaluation (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Subject Files Labor through Office of Defense Mobilization (Box 18)
  - Labor (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Labor Standards (Canadian) (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Laws and Legislation (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Legislative Activities (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Lobbying (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Manpower (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Merit and Service ratings (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - NLRB (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Non-ESA Organizations (Miscellaneous) (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Office of Defense Mobilization (Box 18, Folder 10)
- Subject Files Office of Defense Mobilization through Security (Box 19)
  - Office of Defense Mobilization (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Organizing (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Public Relations (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Publications (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Publicity (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Recruiting Activities (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Right to Work (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Salary Decontrol of Engineers (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Salary Surveys (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Security (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Subject Files Security through Survey of Colleges (Box 20)
  - Security (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Speeches (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Survey of Colleges (Box 20, Folder 3)
- Subject Files Training through Wright Aeronautical Corporation Miscellaneous publications and photographs (Box 21)
  - Training (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - United Auto Workers (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - United Labor Movement (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - United Steelworkers of America (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - University Relations (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Utilization (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Vocational Guidance Requests (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Working Engineers Conference (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Wright Aeronautical Corporation (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous publications and photographs (Box 21, Folder 10)